<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>J. Antonio Guzmán Q. on J. Antonio Guzmán Q.</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in J. Antonio Guzmán Q. on J. Antonio Guzmán Q.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/2019/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/post/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am Ph.D. candidate and Vanier Scholar at the Earth and Atmospheric Sciences Department, University of Alberta. My current research is associated to the develop of methods that help to detect and understand the role of lianas in neotropical ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am passionate about data, especially the type of data that involve ecology, physiology and remote sensing information. Throughout my interdisciplinary career I have been working in fields such as geographic information systems, remote sensing, ecology, physiology, and modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always open to work-collaborate with people in topics associated with my reseach. Therefore, do not hesitate to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biologist by training, data lover by vocation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J. Antonio Guzmán Q.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ph.D. candidate – Vanier Scholar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth and Atmospherics Sciences Department&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Alberta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edmonton, Canada&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0721-148X&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ORCID&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.es/citations?user=Ev3ofxwAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=es&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/J_Antonio_Guzman_Q&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Rivard, B., Sánchez-Azofeifa, GA. (2018) Discrimination of liana and tree leaves from a Neotropical Dry Forest using visible-near infrared and longwave infrared reflectance spectra. Remote Sensing of the Environment. 219: 135-144. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0034425718304620&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Sánchez-Azofeifa, GA., Rivard, B. (2018) Differences in leaf temperature between lianas and trees in the Neotropical canopy. Forest. 9(6) 307. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4907/9/6/307&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rankine, C., Sánchez-Azofeifa, GA., &lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Espirito Santo, M., Sharp, I. (2017) Comparing MODIS and Near-Surface Vegetation Indexes for monitoring tropical dry forest phenology along a successional gradient using optical phenology towers. Environmental Research Letters. 12(10): 105007. &lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1748-9326/aa838c&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sánchez-Azofeifa, GA, &lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Campos, CA, Castro, S., Garcia-Millan, V., Nightingale, J, Rankine, C. (2017) Twenty-first century remote sensing technologies are revolutionizing the study of tropical forests. Biotropica. 49(5): 604-619. &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/btp.12454&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sánchez-Azofeifa, GA., &lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Vega-Araya, M., Campos-Vargas, C., Durán, S., D’Souzaa, N., Gianoli, T., Portillo-Quintero, C., Sharpa, I. (2017) Can Terrestrial Laser Scanner (TLS) and hemispherical photographs predict Tropical Dry Forest Succession with liana abundance?. Biogeosciences. 14(4): 977-988. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biogeosciences.net/14/977/2017/&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Cordero, RA. (2016) Neighborhood structure and light availability influence the variations in plant design of shrubs in two cloud forests of different successional status. Annals of Botany. 118(1): 23-24. &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/aob/article/118/1/23/2196106&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Cordero, RA. (2016) Neighborhood structure influences the convergence in light capture efficiency and carbon gain: An architectural approach for cloud forest shrubs. Tree Physiology. 36(6): 712-724. &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/treephys/article/36/6/712/1753433&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Cordero, RA., Corea, E. (2016) Biomass allocation and gas exchange are affected by light conditions in endangered Cedrela salvadorensis (Meliaceae) seedlings. International Journal of Tropical Biology and Conservation. 64(3): 1143-1154. &lt;a href=&#34;https://revistas.ucr.ac.cr/index.php/rbt/article/view/19606&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Vega, H. (2015) Is forest cover conserved and restored by protected areas?: The case of two wild protected areas in the Central Pacific of Costa Rica. International Journal of Tropical Biology and Conservation. 63(3):579-590. &lt;a href=&#34;https://revistas.ucr.ac.cr/index.php/rbt/article/view/15814&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt; (2015) Ecological advantage of the leaf heteroblasty traits in Costus pulverulentus (Costaceae). Botany. 93(3): 151-158. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nrcresearchpress.com/doi/abs/10.1139/cjb-2014-0157#.XJBxpShKhPY&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Rodríguez-Corrales (2014) Efecto de la regeneración del bosque nuboso sobre la morfología floral y polinización del arbusto heterostílico Palicourea padifolia (Rubiaceae). Cuadernos de Investigacion UNED. 6: 197-204. &lt;a href=&#34;https://investiga.uned.ac.cr/revistas/index.php/cuadernos/article/viewFile/305/517&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guzmán, JA.&lt;/strong&gt;, Cordero, RA. (2013) Growth and photosynthetic performance of five tree seedlings species in response to natural light regimes from the Central Pacific of Costa Rica. International Journal of Tropical Biology and Conservation. 3: 1433-1444. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/449/44930116034.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For conference presentations take a look to my CV.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research and Projects</title>
      <link>/categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/categories/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;detection-contribution-and-local-variability-of-lianas-and-trees-in-the-neotropical-dry-forest&#34;&gt;Detection, contribution, and local variability of lianas and trees in the Neotropical dry forest.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is part of my Ph.D. thesis under the supervision of Dr. Arturo Sanchez at the University of Alberta. The NSERC of the Government of Canada currently funds it. In general, the project looks to create interdisciplinary approaches that help to evaluate the local variability, detect the presence, and quantify the contribution of lianas and trees in the Tropical Dry Forest (TDF). These interdisciplinary are being created linking fields such as remote sensing, plant physiology, ecology, and modeling. Specifically, this reseach aims to answer the following questions: i) how is the leaf temperature variation of lianas and trees at the canopy, and how this variation may affect the ecosystem productivity? ii) Is the detection of lianas and trees based on long-wave infrared signatures a better approach than the conventional detection using visible-near infrared signatures? iii) How is the relationship between spectral signatures and functional traits of leaves of lianas and trees, and how this relationship may affect the upscale of information to ecosystems? And iv) how much is the contribution of lianas and trees to the overall ecosystem productivity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results of this project have already been published and presented in congresses (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4907/9/6/307&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Guzmán et al. 2018&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0034425718304620&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Guzmán et al. 2018&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018EGUGA..20..775G&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Guzmán et al. 2018&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software develpment</title>
      <link>/code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;rtls&#34;&gt;rTLS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Antguz/rTLS&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rTLS&lt;/a&gt; is an R package that compiles a series of tools to process and calculate metrics on point clouds derived from terrestrial LiDAR (Light Detection and Ranging) data. This started as a personal hobby, but due to its current use, we decided to formalize their routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This package is carried out also by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ualberta.ca/faculties/centresinstitutes/centre-for-earth-observation-sciences/participants/arturo&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Arturo Sanchez&lt;/a&gt; (University of Alberta) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ronnyhdez.rbind.io/&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ronny Hernandez&lt;/a&gt;. The current development of rTLS is focussed on four major processes applied on point clouds: i) filtering, ii) voxelization and their visualization, iii) point neighborhood features, and iv) optimal voxel or sphere size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look to its current state at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Antguz/rTLS&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; as well as to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/333204427_Relationship_between_tree_architectural_metrics_and_its_fractal_dimension_using_Terrestrial_Laser_Scanning&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt; presented at the TLS in Forest Ecology conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>